Tonight on "secrets declassified."
the close calls that nearly
triggered armageddon
and the doomsday plans
designed to survive it.
From the Soviet secret nuclear train...
It looks like a normal railway car.
but on the inside is armageddon on rails.
To NATO war games that
pushed the kremlin to red alert.
The Soviets could have nukes
in the air within 30 minutes.
Or a Soviet submariner standing alone
to prevent nuclear apocalypse.
If he just follows orders.
the planet is done.
These are the astonishing
and sometimes terrible things
done by governments and
the people who work for them.
It's time to bring them to light.
Watch Online Movies and Series for FREE
www.osdb.link/lm
A moving target is harder to hit.
So when the kremlin wants to shield
its nuclear launch sites
from a U.S. first strike.
it doesn't just camouflage them.
It puts them on wheels.
It's late 1983. and the
kremlin is panicking.
The U.S. has just deployed
new pershing ii missiles
in west Germany.
And the Soviets believe
these missiles can hit
Moscow in under 10 minutes.
The communists are
concerned that a surprise attack
could take out all of their nuclear silos
before they have an
opportunity to counterattack.
So the Soviets need a
new mobile missile system
that they can hide from the U.S.
And launch from anywhere.
Soviet war planners find a solution
the Soviet rail system.
The Soviet union is enormous.
It runs across 11 time zones
and has 100.000 miles
of railway running over it.
This huge rail network is bigger
than the U.S.'s entire
interstate highway system.
The thinking is that. if
they put an icbm on a train.
they can run it across all of this track.
across 11 time zones. leaving
the Americans never knowing
just where it might actually be.
The kremlin hands the top-secret project
to a proven rocket
scientist. Vladimir utkin.
Utkin is something of a genius.
He's one of the best rocket
scientists in the Soviet union.
His team has already built the Soviet's
most powerful icbm. a
monster nicknamed Satan.
Even utkin is a little daunted
by the task before him.
He calls it "amazing in its grandeur."
which I'm pretty sure is
Russian for "this is insane."
Utkin now has to design a missile that
can be safely launched
not from a concrete silo
but from a train.
At the time. the Soviet union is using
what's called a hot
launch for icbm rockets.
Basically. this means
that the engine ignites.
and as it does. out
come the exhaust fumes.
and that's what's firing
the rocket off into the air.
These fumes coming
out of the rocket can reach
temperatures similar to
that at the surface of the sun.
around 10.000 degrees fahrenheit.
So what you're going to end up with
is tracks and railroad cars
that have been reduced
to puddles of liquid metal.
So utkin developed something
called a cold launch. and
this uses compressed gas
to launch the rocket instead.
Basically. think of it like popping the cork
on a champagne bottle.
Once it's safely in the air
and away from the railroad car.
it fires up its conventional
engines. and off it goes.
It's a win for utkin.
but now he faces another challenge.
Normal icbms are just too big to fit
in a Soviet train carriage.
To stay hidden. utkin needs to fit
his new missile system inside
a standard sized freight car.
That's a problem.
Freight cars are about 80 feet long.
and Satan is 120 feet long.
The math just doesn't work.
Utkin's solution is ingenious.
Now. utkin can't shrink the rocket.
nor can he expand the freight car.
However. he could do
something with the nose.
So he decides to make
the nose collapsible.
He creates a kind of origami design
made of corrugated metal.
which folds down inside the rocket
like an accordion.
Once it's launched.
compressed gases
reinflate the nose cone.
returning it to its perfect
aerodynamic shape.
Utkin calls his new missle the molodets.
Russian for "good job."
Now he just needs a train to put it on.
So the Soviets create what is known
as the combat railway missile system.
It looks completely
ordinary on the outside.
but it's got a missile on the inside.
This is armageddon on wheels.
When it's time for the missiles to launch.
the first thing that happens
is hydraulic legs extend
out of the train and
touch down on the ground
in order to stabilize the train car.
An arm comes out of the top
to move any power lines out of the way.
The roof splits open. and the
molodets missile goes vertical
and is ready to launch.
Starting in 1987. the Soviets built 12
top secret nuclear ghost trains.
which patrolled the railways for years.
completely unknown to
the public. but not to the CIA.
Only in 1999. the CIA
declassifies its files
on the apocalypse express.
The files show that the CIA
did know about these trains
from their spies back in the 1980s.
The files also revealed
that the Soviet camouflage
was startlingly effective.
The U.S. knew that the trains existed.
But frustratingly. they couldn't find them.
So even if the U.S.
struck all of their fixed silos.
the Soviets would still be able to launch
a devastating retaliatory strike
from their hidden nuclear trains.
The system worked perfectly.
From doomsday trains
to doomsday planes.
when nuclear missiles start flying.
most governments head underground.
But not the U.S. president.
He heads to a command center built
to survive armageddon.
one that hides 30.000 feet up in the air.
In the aftermath of the
attacks of September 11th.
there is absolute panic.
and a bigger question starts to form.
Will other attacks be coming?
Just minutes after the
assault on the Pentagon.
observers in the capital are terrified
by another potential threat in the sky.
People spot this mysterious aircraft
circling above Washington D.C..
like it's watching over
the city in lockdown.
The aircraft looks like a jumbo jet
with one key difference.
If you look at the plane
and you compare it
to a traditional 747.
there's a big hump on
the back of the plane.
Confusion turns to fear.
News agencies scramble
to find out if this aircraft
is friend or foe.
To calm the public.
Pentagon sources come clean.
The plane is one of theirs.
It's president George
w. Bush's wartime ride.
the e-4b. known to insiders
as the doomsday plane.
This is essentially a nuclear
command and control in the air.
Now president bush's secret
apocalypse escape machine
has been exposed to the world.
With president bush in Florida.
its 9/11 mission is a mystery.
People wonder if the government knew
something was going to happen
and launched the
doomsday plane in advance.
But in reality. it just so
happens that the doomsday plane
is actually engaged in a standard drill
while the attacks are ongoing.
Now the press and public want to know
more about the plane.
Is the strange hump
concealing a weapon system?
The government decides to open up.
The administration gives
journalists permission
to film inside so the public
can see the inner workings
of the doomsday plane.
The e-4b doomsday
plane's been in service
out of the public eye since 1980.
Now the government
reveals it is a fully functional
Pentagon in the sky.
The doomsday plane can
support up to 112 personnel.
You've got a command
center. a conference room.
even a briefing room where
the president can address
whatever's left of the nation.
Further back. you've
got the operations area.
where 30 specialists
sit glued to their screens.
monitoring intel and the status
of every U.S. asset worldwide.
One way to think of this thing
is like an underground
bunker with wings.
The Pentagon also reveals what's inside
the mysterious hump.
It's the plane's vital heart.
allowing the president to
command a nuclear war
from the skies.
Inside that hump is
the most sophisticated
communication suite that's
ever been put into the air.
It has 67 satellite dishes to ensure that.
even if one form of communication fails.
there are lots of backups.
The hump allows the president
to speak to anybody. anywhere
across the surface of the world.
as long as they can answer a phone.
If world war III breaks out.
the most important people
for the president to contact
may not be on the surface
but lurking deep down at
the bottom of the ocean.
Coiled up in the belly
of the doomsday plane
is a 5-mile-long wire antenna.
And in a worst-case scenario.
it can be unspooled behind the aircraft.
The wire transmits very
low frequency radio signals.
These radio signals are the only ones
capable of penetrating
beneath the surface of the water
to communicate with U.S.
nuclear armed submarines.
This simple wire lets the president
give the subs that final
apocalyptic order to
retaliate and unleash hell.
So even if the nation is a graveyard.
its capacity for vengeance
is very much alive.
The tragedy of 9/11
exposed the president's
top secret e-4b doomsday
plane to the public.
It's still on duty
but in a world of heightened tensions.
In 2024. the air force
awards a $13 billion contract
to create an upgraded replacement.
The details of those improvements
remain a tightly guarded secret.
Coming up. the Pentagon builds
a wonder weapon so
dangerous. they don't dare test it.
This monster is an apocalypse machine
powered by an
unshielded nuclear reactor.
And later. on the most
dangerous day in history.
a lone Soviet submariner must
decide the fate of the planet.
If he gives the word. he
could start world war III.
Nuclear weapons are designed
to instill fear into the enemy.
But in the 1950s. the U.S.
builds an apocalypse machine
of such awesome
power. even its makers are
terrified to test it.
They call it the flying crowbar.
By 1957. in Washington.
there's a new paranoia.
The Soviets have just introduced
the world's first icbm.
or intercontinental ballistic missile.
So now the Soviets are
capable of striking us first
before we can retaliate.
The Pentagon decides
they need a wonder weapon.
They want something so
terrifyingly overwhelming
that Moscow won't even
dare start a war with the U.S.
They turn to the home of the h-bomb.
Lawrence liver more labs in California.
At liver more. they hand the responsibility
for creating this monster machine
to 37-year-old associate
director Ted merkle.
Merkle assembles a dream team.
the sharpest engineers and
nuclear scientists he can find.
Their job is to invent the most
devastating weapon possible.
The stakes are so high.
he's given a budget
of $230 million a year
in today's money to
bring this vision to life.
The result should be so hellishly deadly
that the mission is
codenamed after the Roman god
of the underworld. project pluto.
Merkle envisions a
missile-bomber hybrid
with no human crew. like a
gigantic nuclear-armed drone.
He wants it to be able to
lurk for days at high altitude.
And he wants to pack
not 1. but 16 nukes.
Soon merkle settles on
a design for the weapon
based on a stainless steel
shell nearly 100 feet long.
It's brutally simple.
designed for destruction.
so merkle calls it the flying crowbar.
First. the crowbar needs
a game-changing engine
to make it airborne.
To keep it in the air for days.
carrying 50.000 pounds of bombs.
merkle comes up with
a solution straight out
of atomic-age science fiction.
He's going to power the
crowbar using a nuclear reactor.
Typically. a nuclear reactor has
a lot of shielding so that people are
protected from the
radiation that it produces.
But all that shielding is just
too darn heavy for a missile.
And given that this aircraft is unmanned.
merkle decides to just ditch the shielding
and save all that weight.
So now you have an
unshielded nuclear reactor.
By the early 1960s. merkle's team has
a full-scale engine prototype ready.
Now they need to test it.
You can't just fire up
an unshielded nuclear reactor anywhere.
You need a place where you can make
a big. giant nuclear wasteland.
So they find a location of 8 square miles
in jackass flats. Nevada.
Once the reactor starts.
the radiation will make it deadly.
Merkle's team builds a
thick-walled concrete bunker
for the reactor to be tested inside of
and a second concrete bunker
for his team to observe the tests.
To solve the problem of
how to move the reactor
once it's running hot.
they build a two-mile railroad track
and its very own
remote-controlled rail car
to move it into position.
On may 22. 1964. the flying crowbar's
full-sized nuclear reactor engine rolls out
for its make-or-break test.
The engine is a monster... 9 feet long.
5 feet in diameter.
weighing 10.000 pounds.
When the test starts.
the roar is deafening.
The reactor glows as
it hits 2.500 degrees.
That's so hot that it melts lead bricks
placed under the tracks.
The test lasts for just five minutes.
Project pluto's nuclear-powered
engine is a success.
Once it's been deployed.
it will drive the crowbar at mach 3
on an apocalyptic multi-stage attack run.
So there are four big threats associated
with the flying crowbar.
Number one is the
shock wave it produces.
Because the weapon
is traveling at mach 3.
it's producing a shock wave
that can flatten buildings.
Number two is the
unshielded nuclear reactor
that's powering it.
When it's flying. it's. of course. leaving
a path of radioactivity as it flies.
It's carrying a payload
of 16 nuclear weapons.
It can drop them one at a time.
each with the power to destroy a city.
And lastly. the crowbar itself is a bomb.
So it can be programmed
to target one final bullseye
and take it out.
It will be horrifyingly efficient.
The nuclear reactor
engine works on the ground.
Now the pluto team needs to flight test
the flying crowbar in real-world skies.
Where on earth can you flight
test a weapon that devastating?
The Nevada test range is
way too close to Las Vegas.
and even the pacific
test areas are too risky.
While the pluto team are grappling
with this thorny problem.
a newer. simpler missile
steals the crowbar's thunder.
While it was under development.
we finished the development
of our minuteman
intercontinental ballistic missile.
Once we had the minuteman.
we didn't really need
the flying crowbar any longer.
Only months after a
successful reactor test.
project pluto is quietly canceled.
It has cost the equivalent of $2 billion.
Project pluto is not only
shockingly expensive.
it's a totally indiscriminate
weapon of mass destruction.
So the government buries the details
under top secret
classification for decades.
Finally. in 2015. the
department of energy
and the air force declassify
an extraordinary document.
It details how truly deadly
the flying crowbar would have been.
It shows the united states
government was willing
to try just about anything
to give it an advantage
over the Soviet union.
Project pluto would have been one
of the most devastating
weapons ever created.
Coming up. during
the Cuban missile crisis.
a Soviet sub with nukes on board
surfaces in the middle
of the U.S. battle fleet.
The two crews are basically
staring each other down.
In the darkest hour of
the Cuban missile crisis.
the future of humanity hangs
on a single Soviet submariner
stranded beneath the waves
in order to fire a nuclear torpedo.
It's October 1962.
Soviet premier nikita khrushchev has
managed to have intermediate-range
ballistic missiles placed in Cuba.
just 100 miles off the U.S. coast.
The Soviet Navy is also establishing
a submarine base at Cuba.
To reinforce the undercover
Soviet forces there.
khrushchev orders the
foxtrot class submarine b-59
to sail in secret to the island.
Its captain is a man
named Valentin savitsky.
Also on board is the
cool headed 36-year-old
commodore vasiliy arkhipov.
For this special mission.
b-59 is packing an extra punch.
Alongside conventional weapons.
it's loaded with a single nuclear torpedo
capable of destruction
on par with Hiroshima.
As b-59 is crossing the Atlantic.
U.S. spy planes spot the secret nukes
khrushchev has smuggled into Cuba.
and all hell breaks loose.
President Kennedy
orders the Navy to surround
the island with warships.
Now the submarine is heading straight
into the Cuban missile crisis.
Soon. destroyer escorts
and anti-submarine units
head to Cuban waters to stop
any Soviet reinforcements
from getting through.
What this means for the b-59
mission is that now they are
sailing into a vastly
more dangerous situation
than the one that they
thought they were sailing into
when they departed the Soviet union.
The U.S. Navy is watching
the seas around Cuba.
hunting for Soviet subs.
On October 27th. the b-59 gets spotted.
Its secret mission is exposed.
and the most dangerous
day in history begins.
B-59 is running for its life.
pursued by U.S. destroyers
and aircraft from a nearby carrier.
The U.S. Navy drops
depth charges below.
basically grenades that
generate shock waves
to signal to the Soviets
to come to the surface.
The shock waves violently
shake the Soviet sub.
And for the crew inside.
it's akin to sitting inside
of a metal barrel while somebody hits it
with a sledgehammer.
They're unaware that
the United States Navy
wants to drive them
off without killing them.
All they know for sure is
that there are explosions
going on around their sub.
It has every appearance of war.
Captain savitsky decides that the U.S.
Is coming in for the kill.
He was given rules of engagement
when he departed the Soviet union.
And the rules of engagement were.
if they fire on you. you return fire.
For him. the most effective
weapon system available
is a nuclear-tipped torpedo.
He orders the weapon to be armed.
This is terrifying.
We effectively have a Soviet
commander giving the order
that has all the potential in the world
to start world war III.
However. Soviet launch protocol requires
both senior officers to
agree to fire the nuke.
So now there's just one man
who can walk humanity back
from the edge of armageddon:
Commodore vasiliy arkhipov.
Arkhipov isn't buying it.
Arkhipov realized that.
if these guys wanted us.
they could have had us from the start.
But they're putting on a display.
This is theater... not
shooting directly at you.
but shooting near you.
So he takes these explosions
to mean that the Americans
just want them to come up and surface.
Arkhipov defies captain savitsky.
He refuses to give permission
to fire the nuclear torpedo.
That single moment.
that singular decision.
may very well have
saved humanity's existence.
With the future of the
world hanging by a thread.
submarine b-59 slowly
ascends to the surface.
B-59 finds itself surrounded
by U.S. Navy warships
that are not firing at it.
There is no world war III going on.
as they had been
concerned might be the case.
The two crews are basically
staring each other down.
They're right next to one another.
The U.S. Navy doesn't board the sub.
so they don't find out about
the secret nuclear torpedo.
The very next day.
president Kennedy
and premier khrushchev
cut a deal. and the
Cuban missile crisis is over.
B-59 sails back to Russia.
its nuclear torpedo still a secret.
For decades. no one in the
west realizes just how close
the world came to armageddon.
Then. in 2002. on the 40th anniversary
of the Cuban missile crisis.
experts get a stunning revelation...
an insider's account
that. for the first time.
unveils the one man who
prevented all-out nuclear war.
It makes headlines around the world.
The article reveals for the first time
that vasily arkhipov
saved the world that day.
He was well within
his rules of engagement
to release that weapon.
And if he had done so. the
consequence would have been
the third world war.
Coming up. physics students get
an explosive homework assignment.
Using books from the public library.
they have to build a
nuclear bomb from scratch.
When the U.S. built the
world's first nuclear bomb.
it took a team of a
half a million to make it.
But in the 1960s. the
government tasks a couple
of recent graduates
to design another one.
using nothing but a pad of paper.
a pen. and a library card.
It's a year after the Cuban missile crisis.
President Kennedy is
terrified of the proliferation
of nuclear weapons around the world.
He's thinking it's not a
case of if other nations
will get nuclear bombs but when.
So the U.S. government needs
to find out how easy or difficult
would it be to actually
create a working bomb.
They commissioned Lawrence
liver more labs in California
to begin a top secret experiment.
And the goal is simple:
To see if physicists with no
prior weapons experience.
no access to classified information.
can design a nuclear bomb.
First. they need Guinea pigs...
sharp scientists. but ones
who don't know the first thing
about building a bomb.
They recruit physics phds
David dobson and Robert selden.
chosen for being what the scientists call
"nuclear innocents."
Then they briefed them on their
top secret science assignment.
building an atom bomb from scratch.
Dobson's first thought?
Sounds like a bit of a challenge.
This working group is tucked into
a small office at liver more.
Although they have security clearance.
they don't have access to
any classified information.
And as this is the analog era.
that means that they
can go to the public library.
and they can go to the university library.
All they have access to
are published sources.
But everything that this
working group produces
immediately becomes top secret.
First. the young scientists must decide
what kind of atomic bomb to make.
They've got two choices.
They could attempt to build
either a uranium-based bomb
or a plutonium-based bomb.
Uranium is a simpler bomb.
You can just shove one mass of uranium
into another to create an explosion.
Plutonium is more powerful but harder
because it requires this very precise
three-stage explosion to make it work.
They want to impress
the scientists at liver more.
so they go with plutonium.
Next they hit the library.
As they seek a way forward.
they're looking for whatever information
they can find in the public domain.
And they get lucky because
they find this unclassified report
from the Manhattan project.
So it's kind of like a road map.
But the report is so heavily redacted.
it's of little use in the end.
Once they've gone
through the document.
it's all just nothing but disappointment.
For months they struggle.
even feeling paranoid
and wondering if they're
being set up to fail.
But still. they keep going.
These are smart and resourceful men.
and they understand that
they don't know anything
about explosives. and so they begin
a process of educating
themselves on the subject.
Ironically. they get their biggest boost
from eisenhower's 1950s
atoms for peace program.
which declassified nuclear
data for civilian purposes.
So they repurposed
that data for their weapon.
Soon they begin to build their bomb.
But their experiments aren't
even allowed to leave paper.
When these physicists
want to run an experiment.
they have to write out a very
detailed report of exactly what
they want to know and then
give it to their liver more handlers.
They're never told whether
or not the experiments
are actually carried out.
They just get a report
back with the results.
By 1966. after less than three years.
dobson and selden are done.
They have completed
their plan for the device.
It's too big to fit in a missile.
but it is small enough to fit
in the back of a pickup truck.
And the plans are so
detailed that they even boast
that it could be completed
and manufactured
in a machine shop.
Now the question is. will it work?
Have they passed the test?
No one at liver more will tell them.
Dobson and selden
get sent out on the road
on a classified lecture tour.
Government-approved
scientists and military officers
get a chance to question the men about
their assumptions and methods.
After their final q&a.
their liver more handler
pulls them to the side
and lets them in on a little secret.
He tells them that. if
their design is constructed.
it would make a pretty
impressive explosion.
Dobson and selden
want to know how big.
and the answer leaves them stunned.
It would be an explosion comparable
to the Hiroshima bomb.
a 15-kiloton nominal yield.
They've created a diy apocalypse.
It is a spine-chilling result.
In less than three years.
the young physicists
have unlocked the secrets
of mass destruction.
Dobson and selden's
success has the government
really concerned with
nuclear proliferation.
So they pushed forward
with the nuclear non-proliferation treaty.
which is signed by 59 nations in 1968.
The government keeps
the experiment top secret
for four decades
until reports are declassified in 2003.
Even then. the details
reveal far too much
about how to build a nuclear bomb.
The results of this experiment
are deemed so dangerous.
even when they're eventually declassified
and released to the public.
almost every page is redacted.
Coming up. to hide a
nuclear test from the Soviets.
the U.S. pushes their
technology to the limit.
They're going to try and launch a set
of nuclear rockets off the deck of a ship
in one of the roughest
spots in the ocean.
How do you defend
against a nuclear missile
screaming towards you
at 15.000 miles per hour?
In the 1950s. the Pentagon's solution is
straight out of science fiction...
a gigantic radioactive force field
covering the whole of the United States
created by detonating nukes in space.
By the late 1950s. in the
department of defense.
there is an anxiety that the Soviets can
launch an icbm attack.
The United States is working
on the same technology.
but we're not there yet.
What this begins is an era in our history
during which intelligent
people come up with ideas
of how one might stop an icbm attack.
One of the people that comes forward
is Nicholas christofilos.
He's a former elevator repairman
and self-taught physicist
who's now working
at the university of
California's radiation lab.
Christofilos proposes a plan
straight out of science fiction...
a plasma shield in space.
His plan is genius but insane.
Step one. explode a nuclear warhead
300 miles above continental america.
This will release a
cloud of nuclear particles.
Step two. let nature run its course.
Christofilos believes that
earth's magnetic field is going
to trap those particles
above the continent.
essentially creating a
nuclear shield above america.
If the Soviets were to launch
a warhead through that shield.
its electronics would be completely fried.
This will destroy any nuclear
weapon aimed at america.
The two big issues are.
number one. whether or not
the earth's magnetic
field will be strong enough
to hold that radiation in place
to create the desired barrier.
And then number two is whether or not
it will be created in such a concentration
that it can interfere with
electrical systems on an icbm.
There's no way to prove this in a lab.
The only way to do it is
to give it a try and see what happens.
President eisenhower
signs off on the plan.
Project argus is born.
But it's on a tight deadline.
The U.S. and Soviets are negotiating
an end to nuclear testing.
set to kick in by the end of the year.
To beat that deadline. argus has to be
completed in just six months.
That's not very much
time. so the race is on.
The next challenge is secrecy.
If the United States were to conduct
any kind of an experiment.
launching a nuclear weapon
into to earth orbit and detonating it.
the Soviet union would
certainly walk away
from the negotiating table.
That means that they can't use
their normal nuclear test sites...
not the one in Nevada.
not the one in the
bikini atoll in the pacific.
They want a location that's so remote.
that Soviet spies would never know
the tests have ever occurred.
They choose a spot in the
south Atlantic. far out to sea.
more than 600 miles
away from the closest land.
This is one of the
most desolate stretches
on the planet.
Now project argus must
attempt an unprecedented feat...
launch nuclear missiles
from a ship at sea.
To beat the deadline.
they'll have to do it in August.
That's right in the middle
of the south Atlantic winter.
We're talking about the roughest seas.
some of the biggest waves.
some of the fastest winds on earth.
and storms coming from out of nowhere.
It is insane.
In the early morning hours
of August 27th. battered
by the wind and waves.
the argus team fires off their first missile.
The conditions are too difficult.
The missile veers off
course and detonates too low.
Days later. they try again.
That one also fails.
They've got one last chance.
Their third and final attempt
comes on September 6th.
They launch the missile
and hope that it works.
The missile soars 300 miles up
and detonates on target.
The crewmen on deck look up.
and they see this
beautiful man-made Aurora
stretching across the sky.
It's from the radiation they just added
to the magnetic field.
A satellite flies right through it.
and it captures critical data
and beams it right back
down to mission control.
ready for analysis.
The good news...
christofilos is definitely on to something.
The explosion does
create a measurable cloud
of radioactive particles in space.
This becomes a new
phenomenon that is known
as the christofilos effect.
There's bad news too.
The christofilos effect is
nowhere near strong enough
to knock out a missile.
Project argus ends
up costing $100 million
in 21st century dollars.
Within a year of the test.
the project is canceled.
Argus doesn't work.
but the Pentagon
manages to keep it a secret.
That's about to change.
"New York times" reporters
get wind of the story.
but the government
convinces them to sit on it
for national security reasons.
Then. when government
scientists start pushing
to release the argus data.
"the New York times"
doesn't want to be scooped.
so it breaks the story.
It turns out that. primarily
because argus failed.
it does not derail the negotiations
toward the limited test ban treaty.
which becomes a reality in 1963.
And from that moment
forward. there will be no more
atmospheric nuclear testing.
And there will also be no
more nuclear blasts in space.
Coming up... When NATO
war games get too realistic.
the Soviets prepare to strike.
Soviet high command starts moving into
their underground bunkers.
Moscow is freaking out.
In 1983. thousands of
NATO troops mobilize
across Europe.
Nuclear weapons are armed
and loaded onto aircraft.
The impossible question
facing the kremlin:
Is this another military exercise
or the opening move of world war III?
In 1983. Ronald Reagan
referred to the Soviet union
as the evil empire.
For the United States
to demonize the Soviets
in that kind of fashion
suggested that Reagan was
taking on the cold war
as kind of a crusade.
Many in the U.S. recognize
this as simple saber rattling.
However. in Moscow.
they are convinced that.
in fact. the United
States is on the warpath.
And it's a powder keg of
paranoia into which NATO is
about to drop a lighted match.
On November 7th. senior officers gather
at NATO hq in Belgium.
ready for the culmination
of their annual war games.
an exercise known as able Archer.
What able Archer is designed to do
is to mimic the reality that
most everyone assumes will be
how world war III begins.
with a Soviet and Warsaw pact invasion
across the fulda gap of Western Europe.
which would be immediately reacted to
by a NATO-United
States nuclear response.
Crucially. this is not
just a paper exercise.
For the first time. these
are full-on war games
where they have soldiers in the field.
And they're going
through the entire exercise
as though the Soviets
have. in fact. crossed
into NATO territory.
all the way up to where
NATO would need to
respond with a nuclear attack.
To the Soviets watching.
able Archer soon feels
dangerously different
from previous war games.
As able Archer starts.
NATO rolls out a new encryption system.
And that's exactly of
thing the Soviets see
as a warning sign of
an impending conflict.
NATO forces did exactly
what they would have done
in a real wartime scenario.
They actually moved the
NATO functioning headquarters
to a new location.
And NATO bases all around the world
had their alert statuses
increased in a way
they had never done before.
To the Soviets. that's another red flag
that war is imminent.
Margaret Thatcher and
the other political leaders
are going through the process
that they would go through
in case of NATO and the United States
authorizing a nuclear first strike
against the Soviet union.
Soviet agents in Europe are
reporting this back to Moscow.
and Moscow is freaking out.
As far as they're concerned.
this looks like exactly
the scenario that they would expect
from NATO attacking
them. not an exercise.
So they see the beginning of the end.
In a nuclear standoff. when
one superpower is super scared.
everybody should be super scared.
Hour by hour. Soviet intelligence delivers
more terrifying details to Moscow.
The Soviets can see.
through satellite imagery
and even spies on the ground.
that American bomber
aircraft are loading up.
What they don't know
is that the aircraft are
loaded with training warheads.
Everything indicates that there's
a nuclear strike inbound
towards the Soviet union.
Soviet high command starts moving into
their underground bunkers.
They have their fighters in
Poland and east Germany
start loading their planes with live nukes.
In bunkers across the Soviet union.
icbm crews are preparing
their own missiles to launch.
The Soviets could have nukes
in the air within 30 minutes.
The world is now teetering
on the edge of apocalypse.
but NATO doesn't know it... yet.
At the Soviet embassy in London.
an urgent telegram hits the desk
of kgb station chief Oleg gordievsky.
It's a desperate message
from Moscow to all stations.
"Drop everything you're
doing. and look out
for any indications of
an imminent attack."
They were convinced that
world war III was about to begin.
Oleg gordievsky.
however. is hiding a secret.
What the Soviets don't know is that
gordievsky is a double agent.
He's secretly working for the British.
and he's a very highly
placed asset for them.
Gordievsky realizes the danger.
so he immediately contacts his handlers
in British intelligence and
passes on the information.
Gordievsky tells them the Soviets think
this is a real-world
activity. not a war game.
He's trying to convey that the Soviets are
prepared to retaliate
and might even panic
and launch a first strike.
The warning shoots up
the chain of command
in London. then to D.C.
And news of the critical situation is
delivered straight to the president.
Reagan realizes. my gosh.
they're more afraid of us
than we are of them.
On November 11th.
able Archer is wrapped up.
and NATO forces are
ordered to stand down.
Moscow breathes a huge sigh of relief.
The Soviet war machine
has also backed down.
and world war III does not start.
The whole event shakes
Reagan to his core.
and he launches a new diplomatic effort
to ease tensions.
This ultimately culminates
in the end of the cold war.
For decades. details of the exercise
and the terrifying Soviet response are
buried under top secret classification.
And they'd be there
still. but for the efforts
of one persistent investigator.
Researcher Nate Jones
spends 12 years sending
freedom of information requests.
And in 2015. he gets his response.
This declassified report reveals
just how terrifyingly close
we came to world war III.
From doomsday weapons
to apocalyptic close calls.
governments have long covered up
how near we've come to armageddon.
Only individual human
courage and sheer good fortune
have allowed us to
escape disaster so far.
Do you want subtitles for any video?
-=[ ai.OpenSubtitles.com ]=-